ILR School Alice Cook 100th Birthday Conference Records /4282
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILR School Alice Cook 100th Birthday Conference Records
2002- 2004
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations (NYSSILR)
/4282
2.44 cubic feet
2.4 linear ft.
Records (documents).
8159471
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, February 20, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 05, 2016
Biographical / Historical
Alice Hanson Cook (1903 - 1998) devoted her life to helping working people, and especially working women, on four continents. What she herself called her 'patchwork career' included social work, adult education, labor organizing, a tour of foreign service at the end of World War II, twenty years teaching in Cornell's School of Industrial and Labor Relations, and authoring numerous books and articles. She was a pioneer in bringing attention to issues such as comparable worth, maternity leave, and pay equity, known for both her scholarly writings and her activism on the experiences of working women around the world. Alice attended Northwestern University's School of Speech from 1920-1924, gaining her only formal degree. (She would later receive a number of honorary doctorates, including one from Northwestern.) While enrolled at Northwestern, Alice began her studies of both economics and social work, as well as beginning her lifelong attachment to the ideals of socialism. Early employment with the YWCA's Industrial Department in the 1920s led her to find ways to use the Y for both union support efforts and attempts to organize women workers previously ignored by unions, such as domestic servants. These early efforts with the Y led to Alice's involvement with adult labor education efforts such as the Bryn Mawr Summer School for Women Workers, Arkansas' Commonwealth College, the Southern Summer School for Workers in North Carolina, and the Hudson Shore School. They also led to her first direct employment by the union movement, as she worked for the early CIO's Textile Workers' Organizing Committee. The 1930s and 40s also mark the beginning of Alice's interests in similar developments around the world. From 1929 to 1931, she studied in Germany under a DAAD (Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst) fellowship, beginning her long association with the German system of adult and labor education. She would return to Germany after World War II, when she became the chief of adult education in Germany's American Zone for the Education Division of the High Commission, Germany. Her travels through Germany at this time combined with her own personal experiences led her to become intrigued with questions of comparative systems of labor education. She would ultimately travel throughout both Western and Eastern Europe as well as Asia in order to carry out her research. Alice's academic career began in 1952, when she was hired by the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in Ithaca, N.Y. She began as a researcher in the School's extension division, but moved into a full academic teaching position in 1955. She served as a well-respected teacher in the School up to her retirement in 1972.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4282 AV: ILR School Alice Cook 100th Birthday Conference Audio-Visual Materials
Cook, Alice Hanson; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations
8159471
- 2 video tapes of the conference. One CD with approximately 220 photographs. Three 3.5 floppy discs (PC). Call for papers, financial data, menus, correspondence. (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Alice Cook, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains 3 floppy discs
  - DeVault, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cook Conference Report, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alice Cook Conference, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    November 2003
  - Cook Conference Money, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Women and Unions, Still the Most Difficult Revolution?, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    November 21 - 22 2003
  - Call for Paper, Response, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Women and Unions, Alice Cook Conference, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Women and Labor Publications, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Papers on Women and Unions, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alice Cook Conference, Women and Unions, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Conference Letter, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cook Conference, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - File Copy, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Menus, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alice Cook, Notable American Women, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Alice Cook, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cook Conference, 1993-2002 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Participant packets, flyers, newspapers, correspondence. (Box 2)
  - Women and Trade Unions, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Workers' Health and Safety, Anti-Sweatshop, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Women and Unions, Still the Most Difficult Revolution?, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    3 copies. November 2003
  - Women and Unions, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photos (Box 2, Folder 5)
    2 physical photos, 1 CD
  - Conference Miscellaneous, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Women and Unions, 1995-2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Contributions and Travel Information, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mylene Hega, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Alice Money Accounted for in Spreadsheet, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    February 12 2004
  - Invoices and Budget, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Posters, Alice, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Confirmed and Entered and some Cancels, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Release (Kheel) Cook Conference, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Posters. Multiple copies of the conference poster along with other posters related to the conference theme. (Box 3)
- Alice Cook 100th Birthday - Jobs#1254, 1255, 1256, 1257 & 1258 - (Box 4)